Okay, and now when recording
what I'm going to do is
a demonstration of how to generate an
exercise and, in other words, how to receive an
exercise, how to receive an assignment,
an activity,
solve it and upload it.
To do this,
I'm going to do the following.
Let's suppose that we finish the topic of
the teaching unit subunit.
Where are you?  Here it is.  at one o'clock.
So I come here,
right?  This is teaching unit one.
Okay.  I come here and compress.
Okay.
Copy,
paste.
And then next in an
artificial intelligence
I come and say,
"I'll upload the exercises
that we've done in
the teaching unit.
Look at the code for the exercises.
Look at the learning outcomes
and
assessment criteria.
Propose an activity
to the students
based
on the code
that has been taught in the practical exercises
and the activity
must be about cinema. I'll
upload the file
and let's see it.
Let's go.
Yes, correct.
Yes. Oops, I said that. I hope you
understood. Yes. It was by accident
and what I want is a statement, what I
want is an activity and now I'm going to
be the student, okay? Now I'm going to
put myself in the student's shoes in that I have to
solve the exercise.
Let's see.
Okay, imagine you are, look, a
technical sheet for a movie. Fantastic.
Imagine you are a programmer of an
application
and uh, cinema that needs to save and
display basic information about movies.
Declare variables to store the
following information. Use literals
where appropriate. For example, a
constant for the current year. Do
operations uh like with
Arithmetic operators to calculate how many years have
passed since its release. What a great
idea. This would never have occurred to me
. How many hours and minutes is
the film based on the duration in
minutes? Fantastic. Okay, a
fantastic exercise.
And print the
film's technical sheet on the screen in this
format.
Optionally, add a boolean indicating
whether the film is recommended. True or
False. So this is literally
what you can receive. In fact, it's a
fantastic activity for
unit number one, but I'm not going to
send you this one because this is about cinema and
each of you on the form
will have told me that you like a
different thing or not.
Anyone who doesn't fill out the
form will receive a
standard activity. I mean, the
artificial intelligence will choose the topic, but
obviously I recommend that
you choose the topic. I think
you'll work much more comfortably. Okay,
you'll receive a statement like this and
therefore what you will have to do is, Let's
see, wait
a minute, wait
a minute, wait a minute, wait
a minute.  Where are documents?
Documents.
Here in documents. I
'm going to do the step-by-step guide
to solve or example of solving
a subunit
pun practice.
Okay, let's
assume
a
proposed exercise.
Let's suppose that in my survey I
indicated that I like cinema.
The artificial intelligence
proposes
the following statement,
this one here,
okay? So, OK.
Moment.
Preferences.
Oops,
there.
Okay
. Okay.
Uh, no, wait. The quote. Well,
the quote
was this.
I think it's not going to be, but let's
try it.
Programming.
Ah, no, no, no, no.
Upload, upload, upload. Fantastic. Documents
and uh, save and example
and no, it didn't work. Okay. Okay.
No problem. Look, I'm going to put it as if it
were code and that's it.
Okay? And so you can see it as if it
were a piece of code, let's say. Okay,
so if this is the next statement,
what do I do next? So,
step one,
Solve the problem with code.
From here, I
open a code editor
and solve the proposed exercise step by step
.
So, now I'm going
to leave this here for now.
I'm going to idl. I
'm going to create a new file.
Hey, how annoying.
Okay, and now I say, well, apart from
saving it, I'm going to save it on the
desktop, for example, I don't know,
desktop,
test, or uh, activity.
Imagine you're a programmer. Declare
variables to store the following
information.
Well, first of all, I'm going to create a
doc string.
What I told you before, the
basic structure.
Movie program
Copyright 2025. José Vicente
Carratalá.
Hey, this program
manages movie data,
okay? So declare variables, okay?
Title equals something. Release year, we
don't put ñs, it equals something.
Duration, we don't put an accent, it equals
something.
Punctuation equals something. Okay? And that's it
. So in this case, what I'm going to
do is the  Next. Title: The
Neverending Story.
Release year: 1984,
maybe
The Neverending Story.
Film:
The Novel,
Film.
Year: 1984. Okay.
Duration.
Where did it go? Here. Duration. Duration.
Duration. 102 minutes. Let's put 102
minutes.
Rating. Let's put a 10. So
for now, I've already fulfilled what
we have here.
Now it tells me to do
arithmetic operations to calculate certain things.
How many years have passed since the
premiere? Well,
current year or use literals, I think it
said somewhere. Okay, so, eh,
elapsed time.
The time elapsed to calculate
that. No, Sandro, it's not that it doesn't understand
accents. Theoretically, all
programming languages ​​today
are Unicode. That means
they support accents, ñs, and all that. That's
in theory. In practice, I don't trust it
one bit. Okay? Therefore, it's another thing to
put accents, for example, for
strings and literals, but for
Variable names for compatibility,
in case you later implement on a server
that's in English, just in case you don't
put accents, girls.
I always tell you the same thing, do what
I do, okay? So, the year, the
elapsed time is 2025 minus the year
of release, okay? 2025, which is the
year we are in now. What else?
How many hours and minutes does the
movie last? Okay, so for example,
hours is equal to, a little moment here, the
duration, okay? So,
so, let's see, so this is
duration divided by
and this is an integer, that is, I
want to remove the decimal and now minutes
is equal
to the integer remainder of the division. Hm. No,
of course, this would be duration
divided by 60. Wait
a minute. Let's
see, wait, wait, wait, wait.
Okay.
Duration divided by
60.
Gee.
Duration times 60.
The integer remainder of the division by 60.
Let's see. I want to do a printout of
minutes. I don't trust it.  right now.
Print minutes. Let's see what comes out of this.
Zero. Okay.
Duration match 60.
Duration multiplied by 60. Let's
see,
integer remainder of the division by 6 0.
What?
I'm going to do a trick,
okay? which is hours or sorry
minute duration sorry -60 and that's it.
Let's work with that trick. Yes, yes.
The thing is that it's one hour and 42, but I
can't enter it manually. There has to
be a calculation in between.
Okay. And now show on the screen with
print the technical sheet of the film in
format.
Print.
Title title
comma title
without accent
print
release.
Release year
a moment ago long
time ago
years.
Duration.
Gee. Hello.
Print.
Duration.
Hours.
H
minutes
m
score score
score
of 10.
And if this is correct,
if this is correct and I press F5,
title The Neverending Story,
released 194 41 years ago and it lasts 1 hour and
42 minutes and has a score of 10 out
of  10.
Now, next, this is, I've already
finished the step corresponding
to solving the problem with code. I'll take
this,
okay? And I'll put it here.
Once I have the code for the
exercise solved, I have the code for the
exercise, but not the exercise.
That is, if I look at the
evaluation rubric,
the evaluation rubric
establishes, you have it here,
the rubric establishes how to
solve an exercise. Let's see how to
solve it.
Evaluation rubric.
Now one, a brief introduction. Hello.
Au, au, au. Up.
So, now I
complete
the activity
according to what it asks for.
Where are you?
The
evaluation rubric.
This means it's not on the site. Okay,
where are you?
Okay.
And then I have to fill out the
following sections:
Section one,
section two,
section 3,
and section four.
So
let's see it. Brief introduction and
contextualization.
Explain the general concept
clearly and correctly and mention what it's for
or in what context it's used. And
I say,  The objective of this exercise
is to demonstrate
the basic use of the
main building blocks of a computer program.
To do this,
we're going to create a simple example of
how to generate a simple program from 0 to 100
that manages
the information
of a movie.
And in this way, you are
showing me, you are transmitting to me, not
only that you know how to write code, but
that you understand what you're doing.
So, next,
we say detailed and precise development,
including correct definitions.
To solve this exercise,
we're going to
first declare a series
of variables
that will contain the information.
Two, create arithmetic operations
with the variables,
and three,
properly present the information
on the screen.
Use real code examples if
appropriate. Not in this case. There will be
many other cases where this is necessary, but in this case, it
's not necessary. Now, for a
practical application.
Uh, to illustrate
the creation of a computer program,
we present the following
specific example,
in which we declare
initial variables and process
the data to perform
calculations.
And then again.
Then again. Copy,
paste.
And a brief conclusion. What have we learned
with  This exercise?
With this exercise, we
can demonstrate that it's easy to
create a program with a
basic structure in Python that not only
works correctly,
but
is also
readable,
and that's it.
Last part:
joining the previous parts into a single
block of text.
So, I do this
:
copy,
paste, delete,
delete the introductory texts.
And that's it. And this is what you'll hand
in. Look, this is
the first video that'll already be
done, right? Just a moment.
Let's see. Wait, now I don't know where
this is. Here either, but oh well, it doesn't
matter.
Let's see, here's
local host documents,
example.
So, step number one: solve the
problem.
Now I complete the activity according to what
the evaluation rubric asks for.
Brief introduction. Trick trick,
detailed and precise development,
practical construction, trick trick,
brief conclusion, trick trick. Last part: joining
the previous parts into a single block.
And this
is what you're going to hand in.
So, what  What you'll do is
copy and paste it into a form
that I haven't sent you yet, which I'll
send you this weekend. So,
what I'm going to do is go to
GPT chat and say, "Hey, this is my
submission."
Evaluate
the submission
and score it out of 10 and provide feedback
to the student. I
won't do this by hand; instead, there will be
an automated artificial intelligence
that does that.
Okay? The evaluation,
positive aspects, there's a doc string, declare
the variables, and use aspects to
improve. I
knew it. The calculation of the minutes,
duration -60. Okay, that only works if
the movie is between one and two hours long,
right? Look at it, this is what I couldn't
find. Okay, minutes equals
duration percentage 60. Look. That's
what I was looking for. Okay. Good. Uh,
suggestion for improvement. This right here,
okay? Whole division and remainder.
Final grade: 9 out of 10, okay? I got a point taken off
because of that crappy thing I
did, which  It was to subtract 60
minutes, okay? And that's it. And this is what's
going to happen. And you, the
artificial intelligence, will propose an
evaluation, okay? It will say, "Look, I'll give you
this grade and I'll give it to you for this reason,
and then, as I was saying, I'll create it the
other day in the email, if necessary, I
mean, if you don't agree, you can
complain to me, okay?  Knowing,
knowing that in the end the answer
is being given to you by an
artificial intelligence that can make mistakes.
Well, technically, people,
humans, can also make mistakes,
but obviously
artificial intelligences, you've probably seen
artificial intelligences make mistakes,
right?  So, that's why I'm telling you that,
in principle, I should review the
submissions manually once the
artificial intelligence has proposed
grades, but if you see that there's something that doesn't
fit, a grade that you don't
agree with, then you can complain to me and that's it.
We get together, we look at it, and maybe
the artificial intelligence is right and
I tell you, "No, no, the
evaluation that it gave you is correct
for this, for this, and for this reason."  Or
maybe I'm wrong, because what happened to me
this summer when I tested this system was that
I would enter the
correct answer and the artificial intelligence
would say, "No, I'm taking points away from you because you didn't
enter this."  And I said, "Yes, I have
included it, you know? I mean, it's not a big deal
. I mean, there's a
percentage of determination there and I
know it.
With I know it. What I mean is, don't
worry, I'm not going to
blindly trust what
artificial intelligence says and what
mass says, no. There is always work
above human supervision and the final
decision is made by a human being.
Okay?
And what I just explained to you
is how to submit
the unit activities, the
unit activities and the
quarterly exams in all my
subjects,
in all of them.
That means that the first time
you do this, it will probably
take you a while to get the hang of it. That's
true, but once you get the
hang of it, you'll have this for the entire
course, for all my subjects.
When I say my subjects, it
means that obviously this may not
be and in fact probably will not be the
evaluation system that
Alicia in English and Pilar Ruiz will use in the
itinerary for the  Employability. They will
use their own methodologies, their
own criteria, and their own
whatever. I, obviously, like everything I
program, will make it available to
them as well as to the center, and
obviously, they will be the ones who
will make their own free decision as teachers
and those responsible for each of
those subjects. Okay, I say this so
you don't go to Alicia or Pilar now and
tell them, well, Alicia does, and Pilar and
tell them, "Hey, since José
Vicente uses artificial intelligence,
you use it too, right?" I mean, each
one, okay? They do the best they think
within their subject
and that's what it is. So, uh, I'll go for a
moment, I'll go for a moment to send a
message. Okay, or not, or I think
we'll be the ones who change rooms
because that way we leave the room to
Alicia and that's it, okay? So
now in the next hour, in the
next block, in databases,
but that will be in half an hour,
we will use,
uh, we will
use another room. Okay, and now
Next, we're going to start the third
unit. The third, no, the second
unit. Let's see it
here.
Let's see here.
Okay.
Yes, the third unit, which, sorry, no,
the entire second unit is called
using objects. Let's see what
an object is and let's see what objects we
have. Oh, Sandro, where will you submit
the exercises? On a form whose
URL I'll send you by email, but it
isn't there yet. So, I can't
tell you right now to enter https 2/ I don't
know what, I don't know how many and submit it there
. Not yet, but I
estimate that this Saturday night you'll receive that
form, okay? That's why, that
form basically has three elements.
First, you'll enter your ID. Later, your ID will
recognize you and give you a
personalized exercise for you, and it
will indeed have to be in MD format. That's it.
Okay, at first, obviously, since I
just showed you MD right now, well, I won't
be especially strict about it being
correctly formatted in the
MD format, and then later on,
throughout the  Weeks, well, each time, well
, I will tell you, hey, you have to write
the MD format correctly.
Okay, then
we're going to start talking about objects.
And basically, I'm going to tell you that
programming languages ​​incorporate
objects. In unit four of the
programming syllabus, we will learn to create
our own classes and our
own objects. But nevertheless, let's
see, uh, okay. Uh, but nevertheless,
we're going to start working with
Python's own characteristic objects. Okay, for that, let's go
here for a moment to use
objects. Let's go to
object characteristics. And before starting with
object characteristics,
uh, 001
characteristics,
point MD,
and I'm going to say that objects
have properties, which
are static attributes,
they have methods,
which are dynamic functions, they
have constructors,
or they can have constructors,
which is a function that is executed at the
beginning.
Later,
they will have
advanced operations,
such as inheritance,
polymorphism,
or interfaces.
Objects,
objects
represent
blocks of code,
they try to modularize
and reuse. They
are important
for creating
large programs.
And in this case,
we'll see
moment. No, no, no. Let's
see, one second.
Okay, let's
create an example.
Let's instantiate objects.
To do this, we're going to start by introducing
a module that imports objects, which is the
math module. So, let's
import more punyt,
and to do this, the first thing I'm going to say
is import.
Import math. Hey, not here. Let's
open it in idle. Since we're doing Python,
let's open idelo,
programming,
objects, instantiation, and here, okay,
we import more, and nothing happens. For
now, what we've done is import
a library.
From here on, in the syllabus, we're
expected to work with the
use of methods. A method is a
function. So now, next,
method instantiation,
okay?
methods
of an object.
If I import the object math imports, I
'm going to say
print
math
sqrt
square root of 16.
The result
f5 is 4. The square root of 16 is 4.
What we're seeing here is a
method, it's an action. It calculates the
square root. But  The square root of what?
Well, methods take parameters.
Methods have parentheses, and what you
put inside the parentheses is the what.
Okay, what do I want you to calculate? The
square root of, the square root of who,
of 16.
If you want, I'm going to make this example
more spread out.
So, so you can see it better,
I say, number equals 16 square root equals
math. Sqrt SQRT
B number
and print right. It's the same, but it's
divided into three lines, and I think you
can understand it better this way. I declare
a number, calculate its square root, and
then print it.
The methods of
an object are functions; they do
things, they perform calculations.
Now,
an object,
an object has
properties,
an object also has properties. So
if I, for example, a
property is a piece of data, it's not a function, it does
n't do anything, it's simply static.
So now, next, I'm going to say,
e
pi equals math pi. So
print pi. Pi doesn't execute a
square root or perform a calculation, no.  I'm a
[ __ ], it's simply give me the number.
So I press F5 and it gives me the number pi
with a series of decimals that
the program has implemented for some reason.
The idea of ​​this, as you can see, is that
at any given time we can execute,
we can create as many instances of an
object as we want and objects
have operations inside. Objects
know things. With objects, we can
do things. Let's
see. Let's see.
Okay, so today I want to get
to the end of programming.
Okay, today I want to get to the end of
programming.
Okay,
okay. We don't use
static methods yet and we're going to
review it and yes, correct, correct, Sandro.
MAh is the object that knows math,
that is, MA is an object that
comes pre-built, Python has prepared it for us
and within MAT there are
tons of methods and properties. And your
next question would be, what is the
list of methods and properties? And the
answer is, I have no idea, nor do I
need to know. Okay? Why?
Because we'll always find the
documentation page
where  I'm going to put Python Docs and
then I'm going to put mathule math
in Python. Here we have it.
We have docs.python.org,
that is, the official documentation.
And uh, for example, in
mathematical functions I say, look, here I have
this whole list, I have this whole list that
is super cool. Okay, this list
here and from there it begins to
describe each of the functions.
I'll probably die of old age having
used 10% of all this. Okay?
In Python there are infinite modules, there is an
incredibly large number of modules
and each module has its own
parameters and its own methods.
Learning the list of methods and
parameters of all the
Python modules is an impossible task, it's a
waste of time. Don't do it.
Instead, it's much better to know that there is
Python documentation and that at any
given time, when you want to know and
want to find out something, you'll be able to
find it within the
Python application. Let's see.
No, you'll see, you'll see, you'll see. Very, very good
question. Look, I'll take this opportunity to  I want to tell you
that there's something in Python that,
well, you'll find funny, but it
's actually kind of serious. To
start, I'm going to tell you that the name
Python
comes from Monty Python, and that
Monty Python is an English comedy group
, which is who we are here. You'll probably hear them
from the movie Life of Brian, Monty Python and Monty Python:
Knights of the Round Table,
etc. Okay, so, right off the bat, the
name Python itself is a bit of a
joke.
Also, one of the members of Monty
Python,
one of the members of Monty Python is
the actor
Eric Idle, and
the default code editor in
Python is called Idle, in honor of the actor
Eric Idle.
But besides all this, besides all
this, there's a part that we'll be reviewing
these days called the
Python Cen. The Python Cen are a series
of philosophical rules
that you're recommended to follow, not
because I recommend it, but because
Python itself recommends it.
And we're going to read them.
Beautiful is better than ugly. As for the
code, a  Beautiful code,
beautiful code, nice to look at, easy
to read, is better than ugly code.
Explicit is better than implicit. Do you
remember when I wrote a very
long line and said, "No, I'm going to break it into
three lines so it's easier to understand what
each line does." That's
explicit.
Simple is better than complex. It's a
vital rule, okay? Try to simplify
things as much as you can. Now,
sometimes things have to be
complex. Well, complex is less
than complicated, okay? Make it complex,
but don't make it complicated, they're
different things.
Flat is better than nested. Okay, I'll
tell you about this nesting, how it affects.
What I was saying, sparse is better than
dense, okay? Don't be afraid to use
lines, don't densify the information,
spread it out and make it clear. Of course,
readability counts. It's not just about
the program working. It's also
about the code being readable,
okay?  that the code is understood
when another human being reads it.
From here on, special cases
aren't, uh, wait, stop, stop, stop,
enter.
Okay,
exactly, because I saw you, I already have the
first years here,
okay? Now in 10 minutes the second years will arrive
online, okay?
So now in 10 minutes I'm stopping
this class
and I'm going to compile with you, tear off
the rooms. That's why I'm going to do that. I'm going
to see if I remember and go through things. I
don't know if you read my email. Okay,
perfect. Well, you're number two, she's
number three, but now I'll set it up for you.
Okay, I didn't answer you because I knew you
were in class. I answered, okay,
sure, sure. That's why we'll see each other now. Okay
, see you now.
So, special cases aren't
so special as to break the
rules,
but practicality wins over purity. That is,
if you have to break a rule to make
things more practical, you
break it, no problem.
Errors should never pass
silently,
unless you explicitly silence them.
If you're a student and you find a
bug, don't continue until you fix it
. Learn from your mistake. That's what you
have to do. Now, when you're not a
student and you're in a company and you
want to solve problems
as quickly as possible, then you'll
probably want to
silence them.
In the face of ambiguity, avoid the
temptation to guess. That is, don't have to
guess what your program does,
make sure your program is clear and explains
what it does. There
should be one, and preferably only
one, obvious way to do things.
Although that may not be obvious, unless
you're Dutch. The creator of Python
is Dutch. It's a joke, okay? It's
like a wink from a Dutchman
to Holland.
Now is better than ever,
but it's never—er, often better than
right now. Okay? If the implementation
is difficult to explain,
it's a bad idea. Okay? If your program
is difficult to explain, it's a bad
idea. If the implementation is easy to
explain, it might be a good idea.
And now, namespaces are a
Fantastic idea. Let's do more of
that. What I've done here, you'll
see later, is a
namespace. This thing about putting as, whatever, you'll
see. It's called a
namespace. And that ensures that when I
write code, that code won't
collide, it won't crash into
other code. Why? Because it's
unlikely that someone has put
math in their library. And if I don't put
math, José Vicente, okay? And
then that namespace will surely not
collide with any other namespace.
As I said, I'll explain this to you
later, more slowly, okay?
And yes, yes, correct. Indeed,
Sandro, I mean, the creators of Python,
eh, took very seriously the thing about, you
know? About making it as simple as
possible. And therefore, what they're
telling you is that, hey, since we've taken
care to make a
simple language, make it simple
too, okay? I mean, follow that
rule of programming in the way  as
simple as possible, which
is effectively a Zen, okay? I
mean, uh, Python suggests that you
program in a specific way, then
program however you want,
but the Z of Python is designed to make
your
life easier. And therefore, my
recommendation is to read it and over
time, it doesn't have to be the
first week, obviously, and over
time try to adjust to
the rules of the Cen of Python, okay?
Pilar.
Now, as soon as the class is over, I'll go
with you and get you started in the
rooms.
Okay. Okay, see you later.
So, uh, as I said, we're going to take
a short break and room two is going to
use it, uh, she's going to use it for a
moment.
Ah, Alicia's going to use it, okay?
So we're going to go to
room four and for that, and for that, I'm
going to give you the
connection details right here, okay? Give me a
second
and now we'll leave the room.  And
now at 6, sorry, by 6:5 I
meant 5 cco and something, because as I said,
I'm going to go help the profession now for a moment
,
okay? 5 C and C or thereabouts. Okay, I'll
meet you in the room that I'm going to pass you next
and we'll continue the class. Just a moment, just
a moment while I'm getting the
data from Wow. Okay. Okay. Give me a
second.
Schedule a meeting.
Room dam 1 Thursday
when recurring meeting.
Okay.
No end time,
no fixed date. Okay.
Password. This is the thing.
And
copy the invitation. Okay, I'll
paste the invitation here
and there you have it. Okay, so now in
a moment I'm going to close the room,
copy this you have here, that is,
the click for the meeting, the
meeting ID, the password, and now in
a moment we'll continue. Okay, I'll
see. Okay
,
okay. Just a moment, just a
moment, just a moment.
This is it
,  Yes, yes, yes.
Ah, yes, push commit. Yes, yes, yes, yes,
push commit. But I'm telling you, if we're
going to continue with databases now, it's
not like we're leaving,
okay? Just a moment, just a moment, just a
moment, just a
moment, because let's
see,
sent,
Zoom rooms, no.
Okay, well yes, if you have the room,
what I want, let's see,
Zoom room for Dam 1, databases
Thursday.
Okay,
Thursday
at 5 p.m.
Okay. Recipients
for me.
And this is the question.
And now I want your emails.
And you are
from here. Let's
see.
Up to here.
Okay, then I do this,
I do this, I do this.
Okay, then I just sent you an
email.
Indeed, we close the session.
Okay, perfect. We close the session
so that it's free for Alicia and we'll
see each other at 5:55
in the room that I just sent you, both
by email and here. Okay, come on,
So I finish by